Guide to the Elizabeth Elmer Papers, 1959-1993 UA.90.F86
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Elizabeth Elmer Papers
1959-1993
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Elmer, Elizabeth
UA.90.F86
5.84 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
This collection contains the professional papers of Elizabeth "Betty" Elmer, University of Pittsburgh faculty member, psychiatric social worker, and pioneer in the study of child abuse. Records include personal writing, data and case files for a number of grant-funded studies into the short and long term effects of child abuse, and the organizational records related to the Parental Stress Center and its Bright Beginnings program. The material in the collection dates from 1959 to 1993.
Biography
Elizabeth "Betty" Elmer was born in Black Rock, Arkansas, in 1911. She received a Bachelor of Arts in Music in 1932 from Syracuse University. During World War II she worked at a military hospital in Guam as a member of the Red Cross, a role which drew the praise of colleagues and deepened her interest in humanitarian concerns. Following the war, Elmer enrolled in the Smith College School of Social Work, where she received a Master's Degree in Psychiatric Social Work in 1948. She initially worked for family agencies in both Milwaukee, Wisconsin, and Rochester, New York, before relocating to Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, to pursue a research opportunity.
Elmer began as an instructor at the University of Pittsburgh's Graduate School of Social Work in 1954, and it was while supervising students at the Children's Hospital a few years later that she happened upon an incident of infant trauma that would affect a reorientation of her career. Attempting to pursue further details on what she believed to be a unique trauma from the previous night, Elmer was shocked to learn that the hospital had numerous records of a infants admitted with similar injuries. Her initial concern over the regularity of infant abuse grew, as further research confirmed that no legal apparatus prevented the return of such cases to parental custody. Literature on the subject of child abuse was nearly non-existent in the 1950s, and the little that was available was thoroughly obscured by the clinical language and limited audience involved with publication in medical journals.
Elmer moved from the Graduate School of Social Work to the School of Medicine in 1962, where she first taught in the Department of Pediatrics and subsequently, the Department of Psychiatry until her 1981 resignation. Elmer retained the distinction of Emeritus Professor of Child Psychiatry, but was focusing on other professional activity. Primarily she was busy with the Parental Stress Center (PSC) which she co-founded in 1975. The PSC was designed to educate and assist families with abused and at-risk children by providing resources, training and intervention. During her time at both the University of Pittsburgh and the PSC, Elmer conducted a number of pioneering studies into child and infant abuse. The results of several of these studies formed the material for her two books, Children in Jeopardy: a study of abused minors and their families and Fragile Families, Troubled Children: the aftermath of infant trauma. She also initiated Bright Beginnings, a parental education program for similar purposes. In her retirement from teaching and the PSC, Elmer served on the board of directors for Safe and Sound, the Western Pennsylvania Committee for the Prevention of Child Abuse.
Elmer passed away in April of 2007 at the age of 96. Family Resources Inc., a Pittsburgh child abuse prevention organization, presents an annual Betty Elmer Award.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection documents Elizabeth Elmer's various professional activities around issues of infant and child abuse. Material consists of academic and professional writing, case files of child abuse studies, recorded interviews, instructional videos, annotated publications, and various organizational records of the Parental Stress Center, Bright Beginnings, and Safe and Sound, the Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, chapter of the National Committee for the Prevention of Child Abuse.
A significant portion of this collection involves comprehensive documentation of long term grant funded studies into child abuse. Elmer's 1964-1969 Infant Accident Study and the subsequent Follow up Study of Traumatized Children of 1974 to 1975 are heavily represented, as is her later study Children in Jeopardy, which revisits the infant subjects of her 1962 to 1964 Fifty Family Study in adulthood.
The materials are arranged in five series. More detailed descriptions follow in individual series scope and content notes.
Arrangement
Series I. Articles and Speeches, 1959-1989
Series II. Child Abuse Studies, 1964-1988
Series III. Child Abuse Organizations, 1975-1993
Series IV. Publications, 1965-1990
Series V. Audiovisual Formats, 1975-1988
Access Restrictions
Case files are restricted. A signed confidentiality agreement is required for access.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Elmer on February 28, 2006.
Previous Citation
Elizabeth Elmer Papers, 1959-1993, UA.90.F86, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Bibliography
Elmer, Elizabeth. Children in Jeopardy; a study of abused minors and their families. Pittsburgh, PA: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1967. Elmer, Elizabeth. Fragile Families, Troubled Children: the aftermath of infant trauma. Pittsburgh, PA: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1977.
Child abuse -- Pennsylvania; Child abuse; Videotapes; Audiotapes; Health and medicine; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Transcripts; University of Pittsburgh; Child abuse -- Pennsylvania -- Case studies; Faculty papers; Child abuse -- Case studies; Safe and Sound (Pa.); Western Pennsylvania Committee for the Prevention of Child Abuse; University of Pittsburgh; Bright Beginnings (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Elmer, Elizabeth; National Committee for the Prevention of Child Abuse (U.S.); Parental Stress Center
- Articles and Speeches, 1959-1989; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series documents the writing of Elizabeth Elmer during her time at the Smith College School of Social Work and over the course of her professional career. Where dates are available, materials proceed in a chronological order up to the last three folders. These folders contain a variety of information, and have the distinction of having been selected by the author for inclusion in a three ring binder of writing samples. The folders preserve Elmer's original order. Material in this series dates from 1959 to 1989.
  Notes and transcripts of speeches are also included in this series.
  - Smith College School of Social Work, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Growth and Development through Parenting", 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Child Abuse: An Evaluation of a Residential Program", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Testimony Presented before U. S. House of Representatives on the Child Abuse and Neglect Prevention and Treatment Act, March 9, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Outcome of Residential Treatment for Abused and High Risk Infants", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speech at Eighth National Conference of Child Abuse, October 23, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fist article about Children in Jeopardy, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Drafts for second article about Children in Jeopardy, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Materials for third article about Children in Jeopardy, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bright Beginnings Presentation, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Adult Outcome of Childhood Abuse", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Work from Elmer's Binder, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Work from Elmer's Binder, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Work from Elmer's Binder, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Child Abuse Studies, 1964-1988; II.
  This series contains extensive documentation surrounding several of Elmer's groundbreaking studies into infant and child abuse. It is arranged chronologically and begins with Elmer's 1964-1969 Infant Accident Study and the subsequent Follow up Study of Traumatized Children of 1974-1975. Her Children in Jeopardy study from the 1980s revisits the infant subjects of her 1962-1964 Fifty Family Study in their adulthood. In addition to these major projects, two more compact studies are included in this series: the 1977 - 1981 Child Abuse: Evaluation of a Residential Program and the1988 Infant Teaching Project. The materials date from 1964 to 1988.
  - The Infant Accident Study (IAS), 1964-1969; 1.
    Scope and Contents note
    This subseries includes materials from Elmer's second major study into child abuse. The records document the planning and conceptualization of the study, which precede individual case files. The materials are arranged in numerical order.
    - Original Instruments and Job Assignments, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Instruments and Consults, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Minutes, September 1966-June 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Pediatrician Questionnaire [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Analysis of Data Methods, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Review for Final Evaluation [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Review for Final Evaluation [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Review for Final Evaluation [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Review for Final Evaluation [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Review for Final Evaluation [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Review for Final Evaluation [RESTRICTED, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Review for Final Evaluation [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Review for Final Evaluation [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Subject Cards [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Study Case Numbers [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - IAS 106 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - IAS 108 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - IAS 109 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - IAS 114 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - IAS 126 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - IAS 127 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - IAS 151 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - IAS 177 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - IAS 183 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - IAS 201 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - IAS 202 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - IAS 208 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - IAS 214 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - IAS 215 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - IAS 218 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - IAS 225 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - IAS 235 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - IAS 237 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - IAS 240 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - IAS 243 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - IAS 244 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Follow Up Study (to IAS), 1974-1975; 2.
    This subseries encompasses the planning, data, and case files to the project most commonly known as the Follow Up Study. Informally, the study was often described in relation to its component parts: T1, the time during the study, T2, one year later, and T3, further follow ups. This project was launched as an attempt to revisit the subjects of her previous Infant Accident Study to explore the effects of the abuse study participants suffered in infancy.
    - Follow Up Study Proposal, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Overview, T1 and T2 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Overview, T3 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Overview, T3 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Juvenile Court, Child Welfare, and MHMR Agencies [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Teacher and Psychologist Questionnaires [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Instruments, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Family Analysis, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Card Layouts, cards 60-91, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - FU 05 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - FU 06 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - FU 07 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - FU 14 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - FU 15 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - FU 18 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - FU 21 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - FU 23 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - FU 31 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - FU 32 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - FU 36 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - FU 38 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - FU 42 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - FU 45 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - FU 47 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - FU 49 (photocopies) [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - FU 52 (photocopies) [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Child Abuse: Evaluation of a Residential Program, 1977-1981; 3.
    This subseries includes a summary of this grant-funded study which attempted to measure the impact that the Parental Stress Center's residential program had upon the abused and high risk infants that participated. Subject master cards are included in addition to a summary of the program.
    - Final Report Summary, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Subject Cards [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Children in Jeopardy, 1986; 4.
    This subseries documents Elmer's extensive 1986 follow up to her Fifty Family Study, conducted between 1962 and 1964. Elmer attempted to locate and interview as many of the now adult subjects as possible. Included in the subseries are many examples of instruments, consent forms, sample interviews, and study data, providing insight into Elmer's conceptualization of the project. There are many individual case files and participant interviews in the study.
    - Project Presentation Transparencies, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Reading Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Instruments, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Instruments Pt. 2, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Interview Forms, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Follow Up Interview 1, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Follow Up Subject Search [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Sample Addresses [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Second Follow Up Interview, Letters and Directions [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Health Questions [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Follow Up Codebook [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Follow Up Codebook [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Second Interview Codebook Notes [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Second Interview Codebook Notes [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Second Interview Codebook Notes [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Second Interview Codebook Notes [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Tests, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Relatedness Data Notes [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Data Analysis Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Total Variables, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Data, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Follow Up Scales, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - First Article Data, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Forms for CHP [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Forms for CHP [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Forms for CHP [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Forms for CHP [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Forms for CHP [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Forms for CHP [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Forms for CHP [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Forms for CHP [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Forms for CHP [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - C in J 02 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - C in J 03 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - C in J 11 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - C in J 12 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - C in J 19 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - C in J 22 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - C in J 26 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - C in J 28 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - C in J 36 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - C in J 47 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - C in J 48 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - C in J 50 [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Infant Teaching Project, 1988-1990; 5.
    This subseries includes information on Elmer's final study, the Infant Teaching Project. This project explored the disciplinary actions of caregivers in response to unsuitable behavior in infants up to 24 months of age. Physical punishment and the potential for abuse were of particular interest in this context. Included are sample interviews, planning documents, and data extracted from the actual interviews.
    - Interviewing and Planning [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Interview Schedules: Pediatricians, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Pediatrician Letters of Thanks [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Study Data, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Study Data, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Child Abuse Organizations, 1975-1993; III.
  This series documents Elmer's work with local child abuse organizations. She was one of the co-founders of the Parental Stress Center (PSC) in 1975, and served there as the Director of Research and Training until her retirement in 1990. Elmer launched Bright Beginnings in 1982, which included parental training and a phone counseling service for new or unprepared parents. This latter program was absorbed by Safe and Sound, the Western Pennsylvania Committee for the Prevention of Child Abuse.
  - Parental Stress Center, 1975-1990; 1.
    The Parental Stress Agency is a Pittsburgh organization co-founded by Elmer in 1975. The PSC focuses their efforts upon preventing child abuse by strengthening family bonds and training those responsible for child care, and features a number of programs towards this end. Included within this subseries are early organizational records.
    - PSC, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - PSC, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Conference and Lecture Notes, 1976-1986 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Forms, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Volunteer Training, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Contacts, 1989-1990 [RESTRICTED] (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Bright Beginnings, 1982-1991; 2.
    Bright Beginnings was an educational project of the Parental Stress Center initiated by Elmer in 1982. The Bright Beginnings Warmline served to provide information referrals and non judgmental phone counseling to parents overwhelmed with childrearing. Included within this subseries are project overviews, sample promotional literature, an implementation manual, caller follow up records, and an evaluation of the program. Bright Beginnings was later absorbed by Safe and Sound, the Western Pennsylvania Committee for the Prevention of Child Abuse.
    - Basic Program Overview, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Training Workshops, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Consulting and Cost Effectiveness Notes, 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Evaluation of Bright Beginnings, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Evaluation of Bright Beginnings, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Call Follow Up Record, 1990 [RESTRICTED] (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Implementation Manual, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Safe and Sound, 1988-1993; 3.
    The Western Pennsylvania Committee for the Prevention of Child Abuse, or Safe and Sound as it was more commonly known, was a volunteer organization founded in 1988 to prevent child abuse within a twenty-four county region of Western Pennsylvania. Elizabeth Elmer served on the Board of Directors of this organization beginning in 1990. Included in this subseries are meeting minutes and correspondence, as well as an annotated selection of materials from the national parent organization.
    - Mission Statement and Long Range Plan, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Board Orientation Materials, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors, 1990-1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors, 1990-1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - National Committee for the Prevention of Child Abuse materials, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Publications, 1965-1990; IV.
  This series contains publications annotated by Elmer in the course of her research and work. The materials in this series are published by a number of sources and all deal with child abuse, except for a booklet related to fund raising.
  - Publications, Monograph of the Society for Research in Child Development, 1965-1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Publications, Assorted, 1978-1990 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1975-1988; V.
  This series contains both audio and video recordings made in the process of Elmer's work. Included are cassette recordings of interviews with adult subjects for the Children in Jeopardy study as well as VHS and U-Matic video cassettes made for training purposes by the Parental Stress Center. There is also a significant audio interview with Elmer from August 28, 1987 in which she discusses her background and how she came to be an advocate for abused and neglected children.
  - VHS Combo Tape, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - U-Matic Shelby Myers Tape, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - U-Matic Hawaii Combo Re-edited Tape, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - U-Matic Nursing Curriculum Tape, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Elizabeth Elmer Audio Interview, August 28, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - P0 2 Cassette, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - C in J 02, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - C in J 02, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - C in J 02, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - C in J 03, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - C in J 11, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - C in J 12, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - C in J 18, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - C in J 24, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - C in J 26, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - C in J 26, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - C in J 27, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - C in J 28, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - C in J 30, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - C in J 35, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - C in J 36, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - C in J 42, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - C in J 47, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - C in J 48, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - C in J 48, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - C in J 53, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)